# Haoran Wan

Website: wanhaoran.github.io Email: haoranwan97@gmail.com
Last modified: 16 May, 2023. Mobile: +86 18696020789

#### Research Interest

My current research interests are mobile and ubiquitous computing, including designing and implementing ubiquitous and wireless sensing systems for Internet-of-Things applications (localization, smart homes/buildings, vital sign monitoring/healthcare, and 3D human-mobile interaction). Besides, I have a broad interest in wireless network as well. Currently, most of my projects are based on acoustic signals on commercial-off-the-shelf mobile devices.

### **EDUCATION**

Nanjing University

 M.S. in Computer Science and Technology; Average Score: 91.27/100
 Sep. 2019 - Jun. 2023

 University of Electronic Science and Technology of China

 B.Eng - Networking Engineering; GPA: 3.83/4.0
 Elite Class: Liren Leadership Class

 National Chiao Tung University

 Exchange Student - Electrical and Computer Engineering; GPA: 4.15/4.3

 Nanjing, China Sep. 2019 - Jun. 2023

 Taiwan, China Feb. 2017 - Jul. 2017

### Publications and Research

 $_{\bullet}$  Multi-user Room-scale Respiration Tracking using COTS Acoustic Devices

Haoran Wan, Shuyu Shi, Wenyu Cao, Wei Wang, and Guihai Chen

ACM TOSN, May 2023.[PDF]

Extended version of INFOCOM 2021 paper

SCALAR: Self-Calibrated Acoustic Ranging for Distributed Mobile Devices

- Lei Wang, **Haoran Wan**, Ting Zhao, Ke Sun, Shuyu Shi, Haipeng Dai, Guihai Chen, Haodong Liu, and Wei Wang **IEEE TMC 2023**, Feb. 2023.[PDF]
- ALT: Boosting Deep Learning Performance by Breaking the Wall between Graph and Operator Level Optimizations Zhiying Xu, Jiafan Xu, Hongding Peng, Wei Wang, Xiaoliang Wang, **Haoran Wan**, Haipeng Dai,

Yixu Xu, Hao Cheng, Kun Wang, and Guihai Chen

**ACM EuroSys 2023,** May 2023. [Arxiv]

mSilent: Towards General Corpus Silent Speech Recognition using COTS mmWave Radar Shang Zeng, **Haoran Wan**, Shuyu Shi and Wei Wang

ACM Ubicomp/IMWUT 2023, Oct. 2023. [PDF]

- VECTOR: Velocity Based Temperature-field Monitoring with Distributed Acoustic Devices
- Haoran Wan, Lei Wang, Ting Zhao, Ke Sun, Shuyu Shi, Haipeng Dai, Guihai Chen, Haodong Liu, and Wei Wang ACM Ubicomp/IMWUT 2022, Sep. 2022. [PDF]
- HeadTracker: Fine-grained Head Orientation Tracking System Based on Headphones
- Jinpeng Song, Haipeng Dai, Shuyu Shi, Lei Wang, Haoran Wan, Zhizheng Yang, Fu Xiao, and Guihai Chen Springer WASA 2022, Nov. 2022. [PDF]
- RespTracker: Multi-user Room-scale Respiration Tracking with Commercial Acoustic Devices

Haoran Wan, Shuyu Shi, Wenyu Cao, Wei Wang, and Guihai Chen

**IEEE INFOCOM 2021, Apr. 2021.** [PDF]

#### Major Projects

## • General Corpus Silent Speech Recognition with mmWave Radar

Dec. 2021 - Nov. 2022

- $\circ$  Did a comprehensive study on silent speech recognition with mmWave radar, the corpus is formed with 1000+ daily conversation sentences, and we collected 21K+ samples as our dataset.
- Designed a signal processing pipeline, including cluster selection algorithm to localize users' head and filter out unrelated motions.
- $\circ$  Proposed a transformer-based neural network backend with user-adaptive design to recognize the speech and achieved words error rate comparable with video-based SOTA (< 10%).
- This work was accepted by Ubicomp/IMWUT 2023.

#### • Air Temperature Field Reconstruction with COTF Acoustic Devices

Apr. 2021 - May. 2022

 $\circ$  Estimate the air temperature with shorter response time than traditional temperature sensors by monitoring the speed changes of sound signal. Achieve average errors  $0.25^{\circ}\mathrm{C}$  across months of evaluations.

- Combine Radon transform and Taylor Series to reconstruct the air temperature field with decimeter-level spatial resolution using multiple acoustic devices.
- Leverage LOS paths and reflections to estimate the temperature in multiple slots in a car or on the table with only one pair of devices.
- This work was accepted by Ubicomp/IMWUT 2022.

#### • High Accuracy Localization System between Distributed Devices

Aug. 2020 - Mar. 2021

- Model the sampling frequency offset between distributed acoustic devices precisely.
- Cancel the frequency offset and unknown delays in sound playback and recording process between devices in real time, and return the absolute distance measurement without user's intervention/calibration.
- Achieve 0.6 mm 1D localization errors up to 3 m and 1.86 mm 3D localization errors. Maintain the accuracy in long-term without performance drop (up to 8 hours).
- This work was accepted by TMC.

# • Multi-user Room-scale Respiration Tracking using COTS Acoustic Devices

Oct. 2019 - Aug. 2020

- Expand the acoustic based respiration sensing range to 3 m by combining multiple reflection paths.
- Separate multiple users with modulated Zadoff-Chu sequence, and can recover the breath patterns for at least 4
  users in the same room simultaneously.
- o Track users by re-synchronizing the reflection signals before and after users move.
- This work was accepted by INFOCOM 2021.

# • In-air Continuous Hand Gesture Recognition with Acoustic Signal

Nov. 2019 - Feb. 2020

- Develop a continuous hand gesture recognition system on mobile phone with acoustic signal, cooperating with partners in industry.
- Solve the practical problem of ambiguous gestures in continuous using scenario, e.g. scrolling up is similar to the reset process of scrolling down in consecutive use.
- Design and deploy signal processing algorithm and deep learning model on mobile phone that run in real-time.

# Honors and Awards

- Outstanding graduate students of Nanjing University Dec. 2021
- Huawei Graduate Scholarship Nov. 2021
- Principal Special Scholarship for Graduate Students Nov. 2019
- Second Class People's Scholarship Nov. 2016, 2018
- Undergraduate China National Scholarship, Nov. 2017

### SKILLS SUMMARY

• Languages:	Python, MATLAB, Java, C/C++, SQL, Bash, Verilog
• Tools:	Scikit, Pytorch/TorchLightning, TensorFlow, Keras
• Platforms:	Linux, Raspberry, Android, FPGA, Microcontroller

• Domain Knowledge: (Array) Signal Processing, Machine Learning, Wireless Network

#### EXPERIENCE

Digital Logic Design and Computer Organization  Teaching Assistant	Nanjing, China Sep. 2021 - Jan. 2022
Digital Circuit and Digital System Experiment Teaching Assistant	Nanjing, China Sep. 2020 - Jan. 2021
ChinaSoft International Student Developer (Intern)	Chengdu, China Jul. 2017 - Aug. 2017
Chengdu Modern Hospital Volunteer for Elderly Care	Chengdu, China Jul. 2016